<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Capital Region Mesh</title>
    <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Capital Region Mesh</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.150.1</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why Now?</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/why-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/why-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has to start somewhere, it has to start sometime&lt;br&gt;
What better place than here, what better time than now?&lt;br&gt;
— &lt;em&gt;Rage Against the Machine&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Guerrilla Radio&amp;rdquo; (1999)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Capital Region Mesh exists to connect people — not just devices. It&amp;rsquo;s a tool for community, for resilience, and for reclaiming our ability to speak freely and act locally. It&amp;rsquo;s a hopeful project — a reaffirmation of the belief that giving power back to the people isn&amp;rsquo;t just the goal. It&amp;rsquo;s the method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirp Spread Spectrum Explained</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/chirp-spread-spectrum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/chirp-spread-spectrum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-what-is-chirp-spread-spectrum&#34;&gt;🌀 What Is Chirp Spread Spectrum?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chirp Spread Spectrum (CSS)&lt;/strong&gt; is a wireless modulation technique that encodes data using signals called &lt;em&gt;chirps&lt;/em&gt; — waveforms that sweep across a range of frequencies over time. Think of it like sonar: instead of sending a single tone, a device sends a sweeping signal that changes pitch as it moves. These chirps can be increasing (up-chirp) or decreasing (down-chirp) in frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sweeping behavior makes CSS highly resistant to interference and noise. Even if parts of the signal are lost or distorted, the receiver can still reconstruct the message. That’s why CSS is ideal for long-range, low-power communication in challenging environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
