<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Capital Region Mesh</title>
    <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Capital Region Mesh</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.150.1</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.capitalmesh.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chirp Spread Spectrum Explained</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/chirp-spread-spectrum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/blog/chirp-spread-spectrum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-what-is-chirp-spread-spectrum&#34;&gt;🌀 What Is Chirp Spread Spectrum?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chirp Spread Spectrum (CSS)&lt;/strong&gt; is a wireless modulation technique that encodes data using signals called &lt;em&gt;chirps&lt;/em&gt; — waveforms that sweep across a range of frequencies over time. Think of it like sonar: instead of sending a single tone, a device sends a sweeping signal that changes pitch as it moves. These chirps can be increasing (up-chirp) or decreasing (down-chirp) in frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sweeping behavior makes CSS highly resistant to interference and noise. Even if parts of the signal are lost or distorted, the receiver can still reconstruct the message. That’s why CSS is ideal for long-range, low-power communication in challenging environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can I Contribute?</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/contribute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/contribute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Capital Region Mesh is powered by volunteers, neighbors, and curious minds. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re technical or not, there are many ways to help grow and strengthen the mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-host-a-node&#34;&gt;🛠️ Host a Node&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set up a Meshtastic device in your home, vehicle, or backpack. Every node expands coverage and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-share-knowledge&#34;&gt;📚 Share Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write guides, record videos, or help others get started. Local documentation makes the network more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-spread-the-word&#34;&gt;💬 Spread the Word&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell friends, community groups, and emergency planners. Awareness builds adoption.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Do I Join?</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/join/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/join/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Want to help build a stronger, more connected Capital Region?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capital Region Mesh is an open invitation to anyone curious about decentralized communication. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re technical or just exploring, there&amp;rsquo;s a role for you in the mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-ways-to-get-started&#34;&gt;🧭 Ways to Get Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up a node&lt;/strong&gt;: Use a Meshtastic-compatible LoRa device to join the network and extend coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tune in&lt;/strong&gt;: Listen to local traffic, learn how messages flow, and get familiar with the mesh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect with others&lt;/strong&gt;: Find nearby users, join community channels, or help map the network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your experience&lt;/strong&gt;: Document your setup, troubleshoot with others, or help newcomers get started.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-join-our-mesh-channel&#34;&gt;📡 Join Our Mesh Channel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connect with others in the Capital Region using our shared Meshtastic channel:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Our Mission</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/mission/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/mission/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-why-are-we-building-this&#34;&gt;🌱 Why Are We Building This?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Capital Region Mesh is more than a tech project - it&amp;rsquo;s a community effort to stay connected, informed, and resilient. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re a hobbyist, a neighbor, or just curious, you&amp;rsquo;re welcome here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe everyone deserves a way to communicate that&amp;rsquo;s free from corporate control, surveillance, and dependency on fragile infrastructure. That&amp;rsquo;s why we’re building a decentralized mesh network - one that can work even when the internet doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the Mesh?</title>
      <link>https://www.capitalmesh.net/what-is-the-mesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.capitalmesh.net/what-is-the-mesh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The mesh is a community-powered communication system that uses inexpensive &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LoRa&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LoRa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; radios to connect people without relying on cell towers or internet access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several open-source applications can run on this LoRa-based mesh — but &lt;a href=&#34;https://meshtastic.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meshtastic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; currently has the widest adoption and most active community, making it the easiest way to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s designed for off-grid messaging, emergency preparedness, outdoor adventures, and community resilience. By forming a decentralized mesh network, devices relay messages across multiple nodes — extending coverage far beyond the range of a single device.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
